[music]
Hello everyone and welcome to this
session on what's new in app management
for business central. My name is Yostast
and today I'm presenting with my
colleague.
>> Hello everyone, I'm Ricardo.
>> Uh today we'll cover three new features
for app management and we'll jump right
in with our headline feature of PTE
management in the admin center. So with
this release wave, we're adding the
upload, install, and update operations
to PTE management in the admin center,
which effectively brings full life cycle
management for PTEES uh to the same
place in the admin center. Uh [snorts]
to see how it works, let's jump into a
demo right away with Ricardo.
Great. So let me guys guide you through
what has changed in the admin center
with regards to PT management. So I have
four environments here and I'm going to
go through some different scenarios in
order to show you all the new things and
and cool features that have been
introduced in the admin center.
So let's start from this first demo
environment. I want to show you how you
can install a now from the admin center.
So we open the apps page which lists all
the currently installed apps on this
environment. Now we have this install
extension button here at the top. So
from here you can trigger the
installation of a per tenant extension.
So I'm just going to choose the app file
that I want to install. It's this
version 1.0 of this app. And you can
also choose a different deployment
schedule for the installation. So
previously when you were installing the
PTEs from within the product you could
only install them um with an immediate
deployment schedule while right now we
expose more possibilities with regards
to this. So you can not only install uh
right now but also schedule the
installation for a later moment. We're
going to go into more detail about this
but for now let's just keep the
deployment schedule to immediate. I want
the installation to actually kick in
right away. You can also choose a
different sync mode for the app if that
applies. We just leave it to the default
add mode. Here we accept the terms and
kick off the installation just by
clicking on schedule install.
[snorts]
Yes. Great. So now the extension
installation is in progress as the
message says and this is going to
continue happening in the background. We
can always check the operations page for
the updates and I'm going to show you
this also in a moment where you have a
comprehensive overview of all the
operations that are happening on the
environment. So let's keep this
happening in the background. Meanwhile,
we're going to switch back to another
environment.
So now we're going to go into the second
environment here because we have already
installed exactly the same v.0 zero
version of that PT. We can actually
filter on a different view here. Uh this
was not previously possible. Now we can
get different overviews of the different
apps installed on the environment. So if
I just want to look into the per tenant
extensions, I go here and there's my PT
that I have previously installed with
version 1.0.
So if I want to schedule an update to
this PT, then I can just click here into
manage updates. This will lead me to the
application specific details of this PTE
and I can still say install extension. I
choose a different version of this PT. I
want to install an update. So I'm going
to select the version 1.1. Select this
one. And I want to trigger it again with
immediate schedule. Uh or you can choose
a different one. That's up to you. Still
keep the same sync mode. accepting the
terms and I schedule the installation.
So this will again trigger the
installation of the PTE but this time
it's going to actually be an update of
the PT. We're going to inspect the
progress in a moment to verify that the
update has actually succeeded. Back to
the list of environments, we're going to
proceed with showing yet another
possibility with the regards to PT
management. So if we drill into the demo
3 environment and again moving to the
list of apps this time
I still have version 1.0 already
installed of my PTE but I want to
schedule future updates for this PTE so
that they land actually on the next
minor version and the next major version
potentially. So this is possible with
the install per tenant extension
functionality. Again I want to choose
future versions of my PTE to be
installed. I pick version 1.1 but this
time I want to schedule this so that it
happens with the next minor update.
So I select just next minor update
again. Accept the terms and schedule the
installation.
And it is possible to have multiple
schedules at the same time for the same
PTE. So that I install version I want
version 1.1 to be installed with the
next minor update but I can at the same
time have version 2.0 of this app um
scheduled to be installed with the next
major update. So I can just choose yet
another version of the same PT version
2.0. Here it is. This time we choose
deployment schedule next major update
again sync mode app. I accept the terms
and schedule the installation. So where
can I actually inspect that this has
been captured successfully. Now if I
drill into the application details page
here. This is where I'm going to see
that my future schedules have been
captured. Version 1.1 for the next minor
update and version 2.0 zero for the next
major update. Drilling down here on the
status will show me the operation
details with all that all the details
that are relevant for this schedule. You
can always inspect this at the same time
from the operations page. Same thing for
the 2.0 next major update schedule.
So once we have scheduled a PT to be to
be installed in a future moment, for
example, in the next update window, I
always have the possibility to cancel
this uh future installation. Still from
the same app details page, we have the
cancel schedule install. So I'm just
going to click here, confirm the prompt.
I make sure that this is the intended
action and just click yes. This will
make sure this PT will not actually be
installed in the next update biming. So
everything is reverted as if I didn't do
anything. Great. So everything that I've
shown until now is always audited on
this environment operations page.
Everything that is performed with
regards to PT installation and update
and future scheduling is always captured
here. Um as we can see we are currently
looking into the demo 3 environment. So
we have the first app installation
currently already completed because
that's when we installed version 1.0
with schedule kind immediate. So this
app has already been installed and we
further uh scheduled installation of the
update for this app both with the next
minor update. We can see target app
version is 1.1. Similarly, the later app
installation operation is for schedule
next major update. This time targeting
app version 2.0. So these two operations
are going to be reconciled to a
completed state when the next minor
update starts and when the next major
update starts.
Thank you very much for your attention.
So this concludes our demo about PT
management in the admin center. So back
to use.
>> Yes, thank you Ricardo. Um as you start
using this feature, there's a few things
that are good to know. Uh so first of
all, when you're installing new PTE, so
PTEs that are new for the environment
that you're installing it on, um it's
important to know that the only two ways
to install it is to install the PTE
immediately or during the update window.
So for new PTE, it is not possible to
target the next minor or next major
update. On the contrary, for updates to
uh PTE that are already installed on the
environment, you can target the next
minor or major update for the
environment. With the introduction of
full PTE life cycle management in the
admin center, we've also announced that
PTE management in the extension
management pages in an environment and
in the automation API uh will be
deprecated as of version 30.0 which is
scheduled to be released in April 2027.
Um so we encourage everyone that has
been using the old experience to migrate
to PTE management in the admin center in
the next half year or so. And as you
migrate uh we also recommend that you
avoid using both experiences uh
simultaneously in the same environment.
This is because um PTE versions that are
scheduled to be installed through either
experience are only visible in the
experience uh through which they have
been scheduled until the PT has actually
been installed. So if you uh schedule a
PT to be updated with the next minor
update through the admin center, it will
not be visible in the extension manage
pages uh until the update has actually
succeeded.
And then finally for partners and and
customers that are automating their
extension management with our uh admin
center APIs, I'm happy to share that um
endpoints for all the operations that
Ricardo has just showed in his demo uh
are available in the API and that for
partners using S2S apps um to
orchestrate this across all of their
customer environments uh the permission
story has gotten a little bit easier. So
these S2S apps do not require in
environment registration and permission
sets uh to upload and install PTEES on a
customer environment. Um moving on to
the second feature in app management for
business central. [snorts] We have
introduced the ability for customers to
install hot fixes to Microsoft apps
installed on their environments early.
Um with the incredibly diverse uh
customer set of Business Central
spending many localizations industries
uh with many customizations and
extensions installed um it is possible
for issues in Microsoft apps to slip
through to customer environments and not
be caught by our own internal testing
and gates. Um whenever this happens we
are quick to prepare a hot fix to make
sure the issue gets addressed in
customer environments. And this fix gets
rolled out using safe deployment,
meaning that it doesn't reach every
customer at the same time uh to make
sure that this uh fix doesn't introduce
new issues. In the past, customers that
are due to receive a particular fix for
an issue that they're affected by uh may
have been waiting uh for this fix for
several days if they're uh towards the
end of our safe deployment cycle. uh for
those customers, we're now introducing
the ability uh for them to take a
particular fix and install it on their
environment immediately so that they
don't have to wait for a safe
deployment. Um to install a fix to a
Microsoft app, [snorts] you do the same
thing as you would for any other app
update. You go into the app details
page, in this case base application, you
can see a hot fix version has been
prepared. And uh just like any other
updates, you can schedule the update
from the admin center and choose it to
run immediately or during the next
update window for the environment. As
you do this, there are a few things that
are good to know. If you're affected by
an issue in your environment that is
caused by a Microsoft app, um make sure
you know what the issue is and where the
fix for the issue is as well. For this,
you can use the known issues
functionality in the Power Platform
admin center. Whenever we have issues
that affect multiple customers in our
applications, we publish the details
there and as the build that contains the
fix is ready, we'll update these known
issues with the particular build number
that includes the fix. [snorts] Um, with
this build number, you can now track in
the admin center once that version is
available to your environment and
install it immediately.
Also, if you have opened a support
request for the issue that you're
affected by, the support agent handling
your support request will be able to
provide you with the version number that
includes the fix. And finally, if you're
discussing a particular issue on our
business central viva engage network, uh
the engineers or product owners working
on this fix will also be able to provide
you particular build number um to update
to from the admin center. Secondly, it
is important to point out that uh this
is a very powerful functionality for
customers that are affected by a
particular fix. But it also uh bypasses
our safe deployment, which is there for
a reason. Uh so I would recommend that
you only install uh hotfix versions to
Microsoft apps when you know a
particular version will fix an issue
that you're affected by. um for
environments that don't choose to to
install hotspix versions from the admin
center, safe deployment remains in place
and the fix will reach your environment
um automatically as part of our safe
deployment processes.
And then finally, just like updating any
other app, uh updating Microsoft apps
from the admin center may affect users
that are using the environment. So if a
fix needs to be installed during
business hours or during hours that
users are working in these environments,
make sure you coordinate with these
users so that they're aware [snorts] um
that a fix is being installed that might
affect their workflows. Or
alternatively, if you can wait until the
environments update window for this fix
to be installed. And then finally, we
have a small new feature in app
management in this release wave which
makes sure that dev extensions remain
installed on your sandbox environments.
Until this release wave, uh, dev
extensions by design would get
uninstalled during environment life
cycle operations, which in some cases
led to these extensions being removed
from an environment unexpectedly for
developers, meaning that they would have
to go and republish uh their work. Now,
with this release wave, we've made
changes to treat dev extensions more
like PTE, meaning that they will not get
uninstalled uh during environment
updates or other life cycle operations
unless they're incompatible with the
changes that are being made to the
environment. for example, an update. Um,
this should lead to less unexpected
uninstalls and uh should make it easier
for developers to uh continue their
work.
>> And that concludes our session on app
management for Business Central in 2026
release wave 2. Thank you for watching.
>> Thank you very much.